Rhiannon: Children and young people
from the poorest households can be
up to three times more likely to
have a mental health problem than
those growing up in better-off homes.
This may be related to the financial
strains and stresses put on the family.
Parental mental illness is associated
with increased rates of mental health
problems in children and young people,
with an estimated one-third to two-thirds
of children and young people whose
parents have a mental health problem,
experiencing difficulty themselves.
If the family is given support
financially and helped to overcome
these issues, then the potential
impact on mental health of the children
or young people should be lessened.
A child cannot change their life in the
short term, but by getting the right
support from family and friends or even
from professionals, a child can be helped
to realise that they are not to blame,
and they can overcome these barriers.
Physical well-being is a great way
towards improving mental wellbeing and if
children and young people are encouraged
to get involved with physical exercise,
this can help, as it influences the
release and uptake of the feel-good
chemicals ‘endorphins’ in the brain.
By preventing or handling mental
health problems and building
resilience in children and young
people, their future mental health
and well-being can be improved.
A child or young person’s ability
to manage emotions can support or
impede their learning, their academic
engagement, work ethic, commitment
and ultimately their school success.
Schools need to educate children
and young people to understand how
to look after their mental health
as well as their physical health.
Children with higher levels of emotional,
behavioural, social and school wellbeing,
have higher levels of academic achievement
and are more engaged in school.
Emotional wellbeing is a key indicator
of academic achievement, and subsequently
improved outcomes in later life.
Good mental well-being on leaving
school has a much greater impact on life
chances and outcomes than exam success.
Mental health and wellbeing programmes
in schools, can lead to significant
improvements in children’s mental
health, and social and emotional skills.
Well-being provision can also
lead to reductions in classroom
misbehaviour and bullying.
Schools are much more than centres
of learning and children need
an education that prepares them
academically and emotionally for the
challenges they will face inside the
classroom, and for when they leave.